<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is modified by Seth Nielson for creating P-RFC's
    (Playground-RFC's). -->
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
    which is available here: http://xml2rfc.ietf.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
    There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
    An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2360 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2360.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5226 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
    please see http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
    (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
    (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->




<rfc category="std" docName="rfc1" ipr="playgroundStd_v1_0" number="1">
 <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
    ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902,
       or pre5378Trust200902, playgroundWinter201501
    you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
    they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

 <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

 <front>
   <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
        full title is longer than 39 characters -->

   <title abbrev="PRFC's">Post-Interstellar Mining Protocol Request For Comments</title>

   <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

   <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

   <author fullname="Roast My Professor" initials="R.M.P." role="editor">
     <organization>JHU Network Security Spring 2019</organization>

     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>JHU 160 Malone Hall/3400 North Charles St.</street>

         <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

         <city>Baltimore</city>

         <region>MD</region>

         <code>21218</code>

         <country>USA</country>
       </postal>

       <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
     </address>
   </author>

   <date year="2019" />

   <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
        in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
   in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
   necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
   purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
   specify just the year. -->

   <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

   <area>General</area>

   <workgroup>Playground Experiment Director</workgroup>

   <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
        IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
   If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
        which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

   <keyword>PRFC</keyword>

   <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
        files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
        output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
        keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

   <abstract>
     <t>Post-Interstellar Mining Protocol (PIMP) is a proposed transport layer 
       protocol that provides communucation reliabily on the Playground environment.
       PIMP is a simplified, TCP-like protocol. PIMP simplifies the protocol by making
       it packet based instead of bit based. Secondly, PIMP standardizes the window
       size, so it does not need to be included in the packet. Last, PIMP reduces
       network traffic by simply requesting retransmission of missing or corrupted
       packets, instead of ACKing each individual packet.ts, instead of ACKing each individual packet.</t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section title="Preface">
     <t>This document describes Network Security Spring 2019
     Transmission Control Protocol. It draws heavily from DoD's
     1981 Transmission Control Protocol RFC. It both modifies
     and simplifies the original specification with an aim to
     reduce network congestion.</t>

     <section title="Requirements Language">
       <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
       "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
       document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
       target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
     </section>
   </section>
   <section title="Motivation">
     <t>For applications running in the Playground environment to reliably 
      communicate, there needs to be a transport layer protocol that facilitates 
     traffic.</t>
     
     <t>In order to simplify the protocol and reduce network congestion,
     the PIMP window is set to a standard size (the maximum size allowed by
     a two bit number - 65,535 - which is the largest number that can
     be put in the two bit portion of the PIMP packet allocated to "window".</t>
     
     <t>In case of packet loss in extreme scenario, for example, client only sends one packet to server, but packet is lost, both server and client wait for the response from the other side. The ACK mechanism is needed.</t>

     <t>When server receives packer, it will place packets orderly, then it checks the sequence number of packet to determine if the packet is what it is supposed to receive. Once the packet is accepted by the server, it sends back a ACK packet.</t>

     <t>On the other side, after sending out the packet, the client will keep the data until it receives a corresponding ACK packet whose ACK number should be sequence number +1. It keeps waiting for 10 seconds. After timeout, it will resend the packets starting from time out packet. Within the 10 seconds, it will only be regarded as latency of network.</t>

     <t>Additionally, out of extreme scenario, the protocol is simplified by sending back a retransmission request packet for every missing sequence number after the window has been filled. The window is identified as "filled" after a specified timeout, and 
     at this time, the retransmit requests will be sent. In this case, only the specific packets will be needed for retransmission.</t>
     
     <t>If the sender receives a retransmission request, it should send out
     the missing packets sequentially. If the retransmission is not received, 
     the receiver will continue sending out retransmission request packets
     until the receiver actively closes the connection.</t>
     
     <t>In this way, the network traffic is reduced by not having an ACK for
     each sequence number, but simply for each missing one, and an ACK for each 
     window when it is complete.</t>
     
     <t>We no longer need a data offset field since the options field has been
      removed, so the PIMP header will be of fixed length. Because the port 
      numbers will be fixed, these fields can also be excluded from the PIMP header.</t>
     
     <t>Finally, we guard against SYN flooding by having a time out. If
     nothing is received from a client within the timeout, the connection
     is closed. SYN flooding may briefly occur, but the TCB will be flushed
     of any connections that are not fully open each time the timeout elapses.</t>
    
    <section title="Reliability">
    <t>The prime directive to PIMP is reliability. In order for data
      to be reliably transmitted, sequence numbers are used. The sender
      must complete the sequence and retransmit missing packets before
      they are given a new window with the next set of sequence numbers.
      Packets may be lost on the network, and a mechanism for retransmission
      must be supplied. The sequence numbers prevent duplicates, verify all 
      sent data has been received, and provide a mechanism for identifying 
      missing segments. Checksums are provided to recognize corruption of data.
      Retransmission of corrupted or fragmented data can then be requested.</t>
    
    <t>Additional metadata includes the "References" and "Author's Address"
    sections. These elements MUST conform to RFC specifications.</t>
    </section>
  
   </section>
   
   <section title="Protocol">
   <t>
      <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
        from playground.network.packet import PacketType
        from playground.network.packet.fieldtypes 
                              import UINT32, STRING, BUFFER, BOOLEAN
        class PIMPPacket(PacketType):
            DEFINITION_IDENTIFIER = "PIMP.Packet"
            DEFINITION_VERSION = "1.0"
            FIELDS = [
              ("seqNum", UINT32),
              ("ackNum", UINT32),
              ("ACK", BOOLEAN), 
              ("RST", BOOLEAN),
              ("SYN", BOOLEAN),
              ("FIN", BOOLEAN),
              ("RTR", BOOLEAN),
              ("checkSum", BUFFER),  
              ("data", BUFFER)
            ]
                  ]]>
          </artwork>
      </figure>
	   </t>
     <section title = "Header Descriptions">
       <t>Sequence Number - 32 bits:</t>
       			<t><list style="empty">
							<t> The sequence number is in the seqNum field. We will use python's 
              Random module in Initial Sequence Number (ISN) determination. If a packet is an ACK packet that is out of the handshake and just ACKing data, the seqNum should be set to 0 </t>
            </list></t>
       <t>Acknowledgment Number - 32 bits:</t>
       			<t><list style="empty">
							<t>The acknowledgment number is a number that is 1 more than the last sequence number. 
         			This is sent to the sender to notify them that their last packet was received. If a packet is an data packet that is out of the handshake, and just sending data, the ACK num should be set to 0.</t>
            </list></t>
       <t>Control Flags:</t>
       			<t><list style="empty">
							<t>ACK - Acknowledgement field significant</t>
              <t>RST - Reset the connection</t>
              <t>SYN - Synchronize sequence numbers</t>
              <t>FIN - Receive no more data from the sender</t>
              <t>RTR - Request retransmission from sender</t>
            </list></t>
       <t>Checksum - BUFFER</t>

       			<t><list style="empty">
							<t> Checksum will be done using the MD5 algorithm, which takes an arbitrary length input and produces a 128 bit output which is stored in a buffer. In our case the input will be header fields prior to the checksum (last field being RTR) and data. This requires little effort to implement, as there are packages to perform an MD5 hash.</t>

            </list></t>
     </section>
     
     <section title = "Packet Description">
       <t>class PIMPPacket(PacketType):
          DEFINITION_IDENTIFIER = "roastmyprofessor.pimp.PIMPPacket"
    			DEFINITION_VERSION = "1.0"
    			BODY = [
        		("seqNum", UINT32),
        		("ackNum", UINT32)
         		("ACK", BOOLEAN)
            ("RST", BOOLEAN)
            ("SYN", BOOLEAN)
            ("FIN", BOOLEAN)
            ("RTR", BOOLEAN)
            ("checksum", BUFFER)
         		("data", BUFFER)
    			]
       </t>
       <t>PIMP packets include two sections, the header and the data sections. 
         The header section includes the fields described in the header description. 
         The data section, on the other hand, includes a buffer with the data being transmitted.</t>
     </section>
     
     <section title = "Error handling">
       <t>There are multiple errors that can occur:</t>
       
       <t><list style="numbers">
		        <t>Packet loss</t>
            <t>Corrupted data (indicated by an incorrect checksum)</t>
		        <t>*Packet with invalid flags (invalid flag combination) is received</t>
       </list></t>
       
       <t>In case of experiencing packet loss, sender of a packet should keep a timer of minimum 5 seconds timeout before receiving ACK, after which it should resend the previous packet.</t>

       <t>In case of corrupted data, receiver should immediately sends a request for retranmission packet whose RTR flag MUST be set, together with the correct ACK number.</t>

       <t>*In the last case (invalid flag combination for a packet received), such as an incorrect combination of flags, the packet will be dropped.</t>

     </section>
   </section>
   <section title="Technical Functionality">
     <t>
      The "three-way handshake" is the procedure used to establish a connection. This procedure normally is initiated by one PIMP and responded to by another PIMP. The procedure also works if two PIMP simultaneously initiate the procedure. When simultaneous attempt occurs, each PIMP receives packet with the SYN flag set which carries no acknowledgment after it has sent a "SYN". Of course, the arrival of an old duplicate "SYN" segment can potentially make it appear, to the recipient, that a simultaneous connection initiation is in progress. Proper use of "reset" segments can disambiguate these cases.
      Several examples of connection initiation follow. Although these examples do not show connection synchronization using data-carrying segments, this is perfectly legitimate, so long as the receiving PIMP doesn't deliver the data to the user until it is clear the data is valid (i.e., the data must be buffered at the receiver until the connection reaches the ESTABLISHED state). The three-way handshake reduces the possibility of false connections. It is the implementation of a trade-off between memory and messages to provide information for this checking.
      The simplest three-way handshake is shown in figure 7 below. The figures should be interpreted in the following way. Each line is numbered for reference purposes. Right arrows (-->) indicate
      departure of a PIMP packet from PIMP A to PIMP B, or arrival of a packet at B from A. Left arrows, indicate the reverse. Ellipsis (...) indicates a segment which is still in the network (delayed). An "XXX" indicates a segment which is lost or rejected.
      Comments appear in parentheses. PIMP states represent the state AFTER the departure or arrival of the segment (whose contents are shown in the center of each line). Segment contents are shown in abbreviated form, with sequence number, and ACK field. Other fields such as window, addresses, lengths, and text have been left out in the interest of clarity. 
    </t>
    <figure align="center">
      <preamble>The following artwork demonstrates the connection state diagram:</preamble>
      <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
PIMP A                                                         PIMP B
                                                        CLOSED LISTEN
SYN-SENT    --> <SEQ=100><SYNFLAG>                   --> SYN-RECEIVED
ESTABLISHED <-- <SEQ=300><ACK=101><SYNFLAG, ACKFLAG> <-- SYN-RECEIVED
ESTABLISHED --> <SEQ=101><ACK=301><ACKFLAG><DATA>     --> ESTABLISHED
                  ]]>
       </artwork>
      <postamble>
        PIMP Connection State Diagram
      </postamble>
  </figure>
        <t>
        The principle reason for the three-way handshake is to prevent old duplicate connection initiations from causing confusion. To deal with this, a special control message, reset, has been devised. If the receiving PIMP is in a non-synchronized state (i.e., SYN-SENT, SYN-RECEIVED), it returns to LISTEN on receiving an acceptable reset. If the TCP is in one of the synchronized states it aborts the connection and informs its user. We discuss this later case under "half-open" connections below. </t>
        <t>
        HALF OPEN
        An established connection is said to be "half-open" if one of the PIMPs has closed or aborted the connection at its end without the knowledge of the other, or if the two ends of the connection have become desynchronized owing to a crash that resulted in loss of memory. Such connections will automatically become reset if an attempt is made to send data in either direction. However, half-open connections are expected to be unusual, and the recovery procedure is mildly involved.
        If at site A the connection no longer exists, then an attempt by the user at site B to send any data on it will result in the site B PIMP receiving a reset control message. Such a message indicates to the site B PIMP that something is wrong, and it is expected to abort the connection.
        Assume that two user processes A and B are communicating with one another when a crash occurs causing loss of memory to A's PIMP.
        Depending on the operating system supporting A's PIMP, it is likely that some error recovery mechanism exists. When the PIMP is up again, A is likely to start again from the beginning or from a recovery point. As a result, A will probably try to OPEN the connection again or try to SEND on the connection it believes open. In the latter case, it receives the error message "connection not open" from the local (A's) PIMP. In an attempt to establish the connection, A's PIMP will send a packet containing SYN. This scenario leads to the example shown in figure 10. After PIMP A crashes, the user attempts to re-open the connection. PIMP B, in the meantime, thinks the connection is open. 
        </t>
      <figure align="center">
            <preamble>The following artwork demonstrates the connection state diagram:</preamble>
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
PIMP A                                           PIMP B
(CRASH) (send 300,receive 100)
CLOSED ESTABLISHED
SYN-SENT --> <SEQ=400><SYNFLAG=TRUE>          --> (??)
(!!)     <-- <SEQ=300><ACK=100><ACKFLAG=TRUE> <-- ESTABLISHED
SYN-SENT --> <SEQ=100><CTL=RST>               --> (Abort!!)
SYN-SENT CLOSED
SYN-SENT --> <SEQ=400><SYNFLAG=TRUE>          -->
                ]]>
                 </artwork>
            <postamble>
              PIMP Connection State Diagram
            </postamble>
        </figure>
        <t>When the SYN arrives at line 3, PIMP B, being in a synchronized state and the incoming segment outside the window, responds with an acknowledgment indicating what sequence it next expects to hear (ACKFLAG = TRUE SEQ=100). PIMP A sees that this segment does not acknowledge anything it sent and, being unsynchronized, sends a reset (RST) because it has detected a half-open connection. PIMP B aborts at line 5. PIMP A will continue to try to establish the connection; the problem is now reduced to the basic 3-way handshake of figure 7.
        An interesting alternative case occurs when PIMP A crashes and PIMP B tries to send data on what it thinks is a synchronized connection.
        This is illustrated in figure 11. In this case, the data arriving at PIMP A from PIMP B (line 2) is unacceptable because no such connection exists, so PIMP A sends a RST. The RST is acceptable so PIMP B processes it and aborts the connection.</t>
        <figure align="center">
            <preamble>The following artwork demonstrates the connection state diagram:</preamble>
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
PIMP A                                                       PIMP B
(CRASH) (send 300,receive 100)
(??) <-- <SEQ=300><ACK=100><DATA=10><ACKFLAG=TRUE>. <-- ESTABLISHED
     --> <SEQ=100><CTL=RST>                         --> (ABORT!!)
 SOURCE: Obviously copied from TCP RFC</t>
                   ]]>
             </artwork>
            <postamble>
              PIMP Connection State Diagram
            </postamble>
        </figure>
          <!-- ARTWORK EXAMPLE -->
      <figure anchor="xml_state" align="center">
            <preamble>The following artwork demonstrates the connection state diagram:</preamble>
            <artwork align="center">
<![CDATA[ 
                          +---------+ ---------\      active OPEN
                          |  CLOSED |            \    -----------
                          +---------+<---------\   \   create TCB
                            |     ^              \   \  snd SYN
               passive OPEN |     |   CLOSE        \   \
               ------------ |     | ----------       \   \
                create TCB  |     | delete TCB         \   \
                            V     |                      \   \
                          +---------+            CLOSE    |    \
                          |  LISTEN |          ---------- |     |
                          +---------+          delete TCB |     |
               rcv SYN      |     |     SEND              |     |
              -----------   |     |    -------            |     V
  +-------+    snd SYN,ACK  /       \   snd SYN          +-------+
 |         |<---------------           ---------------->|         |
 |   SYN   |                rcv SYN                     |   SYN   |
 |   RCVD  |<-------------------------------------------|   SENT  |
 |         |                  snd ACK                   |         |
 |         |----------------           -----------------|         |
 +---------+ rcv ACK of SYN  \       /  rcv SYN,ACK     +---------+
   |         --------------   |     |   -----------
   |                x         |     |     snd ACK
   |                          V     V
   |  CLOSE                 +---------+
   | -------                |  ESTAB  |
   | snd FIN                +---------+
   |                 CLOSE    |     |    rcv FIN
   V                -------   |     |    -------
 +---------+        snd FIN  /       \   snd ACK        +---------+
 |  FIN    |<---------------           ---------------->|         |
 | WAIT-1  |------------------                          |         |
 +---------+          rcv FIN  \                        +---------+
   | rcv ACK of FIN   -------   |                                 |
   | --------------   snd ACK   |                         ------- |
   V        x                   V                         snd FIN V
 +---------+                +---------+                 +---------+
 |FINWAIT-2|                | CLOSING |                 | LAST-ACK|
 +---------+                +---------+                 +---------+
   |              rcv ACK of FIN |                 rcv ACK of FIN |
   |  rcv FIN     -------------- |    Timeout=2MSL -------------- |
   |  -------            x       V    ------------        x       V
    \ snd ACK               +---------+delete TCB       +---------+
     ---------------------->|TIME WAIT|---------------->| CLOSED  |
                            +---------+                 +---------+
]]>
            </artwork>
            <postamble>
              PIMP Connection State Diagram
            </postamble>
        </figure>
   
   </section>
   <section title="PETF FIX ME">
	   <t>	   
		 The reciever of the FIN packet will send a FIN-ACK. Upon reciept of the FIN-ACK, the reciever
			 of the FIN-ACK will wait for any outstanding data (missing sequence numbers) from the sender of
			 the FIN. The reciever of the FIN-ACK will also wait until any un-ACKed packets they have sent to
			 be ACKed and then one last ACK will be sent. The reciver of the FIN ACK will send the ACK and then close
			 (after sending and recieving any previous SEQs and ACKs). 
			 The sender of the FIN ACK will wait for the last ACK. 
			 If it doesn't recieve the ACK within the timeout period, but gotten ACKs for all
			 data sent and doesn't have any un-ACKed data, it will close anyway.
			 The sequence number and ack number in FIN, FIN-ACK and the final ACK should be the next numbers in the regular sequence.
			 These will NOT be seperate ACK packets. The FIN will contain the sequence number and the ACK number will be set to zero.
			 The FIN-ACK will contain the sender's sequence number AND ACK for the FIN. The final ACK will contain the sequence number
			 and ACK number for the FIN-ACK.
		 </t>
	 </section>
<section title="ACK Specification">
    <t>Under normal data transformation, the active open is performed by the client sending a SYN to the server. The client set the segment's sequence number to a random value A. Then when server successfully receives a SYN, in response, it replies with a SYN-ACK. The Ack number  is set to one more than the received sequence number i.e A+1. and the sequence number that the server chooses for the packet is another random number,B. Finally the client sends an ACK back to the server. The sequence number is set to the received acknowledgement value i.e. A+1, and the acknowledgement number is set to one more than the received sequence number i.e. B+1. At this point, both the client and server have received and acknowledgment of the connection. And the connection is established.</t>

    <t>If the first SYN packet is lost, the timeout mechanism will be called on client side and it will automatically resend the SYN packet once the ack does not arrive within the set time. And if it tries several times, connection will terminate.</t>

    <t>If SYN-ACK packet sent by server or ACK packet sent by the client is lost, timeout mechanism on server side will do the same thing, which means server will actively resend out the SYN-ACK packet once the ack does not arrive within the time. And if it tries several times, connection will terminate.</t>

    <t>Ideally, in the data transmission process, the client would send out data packets with continuously increment sequence numbers (seqNum). If nothing goes wrong, after the server receives a packet with seqNum = i, the server would respond back an acknowledgment packet to the client with the acknowledgment number (ackNum) equals to i + 1.</t>

    <t>In the case that the server does not successfully receive data packets sent from the client, no associated acknowledgment packets will be sent back to the client. As a result, as long as the client keeps track of all the sent packets, if after a certain timeout the client still not receive the ACK for those packets, the client would consider those packets are lost, and thus re-transmit them to the server again.</t>

    <t>The connection termination procedure for a pimp session is shown as following:
    In the case the client initiates the termination, it sends a FIN. After receiving it, the server sends back a acknowledgement. The server waits for application process to close and then sends its FIN. After receiving it, the client sends back a acknowledgement. Then the server closes when receiving the ACK, and client waits until the ACK is received by the server then the client proceeds to the closed state. If any of the packet is lost during the transmission, the timeout function is applied.</t>
</section>

   <section title="PRFC Revision Process">
   <t>Once a PRFC is officially published by the PETF, it cannot be modified further
   for any reason. A new PRFC must be submitted that identifies the errors and 
   proposes to "update" or "supercede" the previous document.</t>
   
   <t>A PRFC MUST use the "update" reference if the changes do not result in an
   incompatible protocol and the old protocol is not shown to be insecure. 
   Changes to PRFC's that are "updates" include:</t>
   
   <t><list style="numbers">
    <t>Corrections to spelling, grammar, and other wording in the document</t>
    <t>Additional details about operations and operational considerations</t>
    <t>Additional parameters or interactions to the existing protocol</t>
   </list></t>
   
   <t>A PRFC MUST use the "supercede" reference if the changes result in an incompatible
   protocol OR if the previous protocol is demonstrated to be insecure.</t>
   
   <t>Approval from the PETF MUST be obtained if approval was required for the original
   PRFC.</t>
   
   <t>A PRFC submitted without PETF approval MUST be revised only by the same PLAYGROUND
   group that submitted the original.</t>
   </section>
   
   <section title="Security Considerations">
   <t>This specification is a documentation standard and not directly related
   to the technical security of any protocol.</t>
   </section>
       <section title="Copyright Information">
    <t>The PLAYGROUND experiment is still new and has not yet developed
    a policy that has been reviewed by legal counsel. However, at present,
    the following text MUST be used in the PRFC's.</t>
    
    <t>The copyright notice on the front page of the PRFC should read:
    "Copyright (c) 2017 SETH JAMES NIELSON.  All rights reserved.</t>

   <t>This document is used solely for educational purposes.  Any citations
   within this document are also for educational purposes and also for
   technical reference.  If any of these cited elements are protected
   under copyright, their inclusion here falls under Fair Use
   provisions."</t>
   
   <t>Student authors MUST grant copyrights to SETH JAMES NIELSON. However,
   they may also retain copyrights for themselves and add their names to the
   copyright notice accordingly.</t>
   
   <t> The final page of the PRFC MUST include a section entitled 
   "Full Copyright Statement" that reads:</t>
   
   <t>"Copyright (C) Seth James Nielson (2017).  All Rights Reserved.</t>

   <t>This document and translations of it may be copied and furnished to
   others, and derivative works that comment on or otherwise explain it
   or assist in its implementation may be prepared, copied, published
   and distributed, in whole or in part, without restriction of any
   kind, provided that the above copyright notice and this paragraph are
   included on all such copies and derivative works.  However, this
   document itself may not be modified in any way, such as by removing
   the copyright notice or references to the PLAYGROUND experiment or
   other associated organizations, except by explicit permission.</t>

   <t>The limited permissions granted above are perpetual and will not be
   revoked by SETH JAMES NIELSON or his successors or assigns.</t>

   <t>This document and the information contained herein is provided on an
   "AS IS" basis and SETH JAMES NIELSON and associated academic
   institutions DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING
   BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE INFORMATION
   HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY RIGHTS OR ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
   MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE."</t>
   
   <t>After the "Full Copyright Statement" the PRFC MUST include a section
   entitled "Intellectual Property" that reads:</t>

   <t>The PLAYGROUND framework and student submissions for PLAYGROUND are
   intended to be free of any intellectual property conflicts.  All
   submitting parties, especially students, are not allowed to submit
   source code, specifications, or other components that are known to be
   protected by copyright, patents, or other IP mechanisms.  Students
   submitting creative content grant shared rights and ownership of
   their content to the PLAYGROUND project.  Specifically, any
   submission can be used in future educational settings including
   subsequent PLAYGROUND experiments.</t>

   <t>Any interested party is invited to bring to the experiment director's
   attention any copyrights, patents or patent applications, or other
   proprietary rights which may cover technology that may be currently
   in use without permission.</t>

   <t>It should be noted that these statements have not been reviewed by
   legal counsel.  Moreover, the academic institutions at which
   PLAYGROUND experiments take place may have additional or even
   conflicting copyright and intellectual property rules.  Accordingly,
   concerned parties may need to contact their own lawyer and/or
   resources at their institution to understand the rights and
   limitations associated with code donated to a PLAYGROUND experiment."</t>
   
   <t>As with the initial copyright notice, the Copyright assignment to
   Seth James Nielson can be agumented the the names of the authors.</t>
    </section>
 </middle>

 <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

 <back>
   <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

   <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
    1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
    2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
       (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")
    Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
    If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
    directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
    with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
    filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->
   
   <references title="Normative References">
     <!--?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0793.xml"?-->
     <!--?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
     &RFC2119;
     
   </references>


   <!-- Change Log
v00 2006-03-15  EBD   Initial version
v01 2006-04-03  EBD   Moved PI location back to position 1 -
                     v3.1 of XMLmind is better with them at this location.
v02 2007-03-07  AH    removed extraneous nested_list attribute,
                     other minor corrections
v03 2007-03-09  EBD   Added comments on null IANA sections and fixed heading capitalization.
                     Modified comments around figure to reflect non-implementation of
                     figure indent control.  Put in reference using anchor="DOMINATION".
                     Fixed up the date specification comments to reflect current truth.
v04 2007-03-09 AH     Major changes: shortened discussion of PIs,
                     added discussion of rfc include.
v05 2007-03-10 EBD    Added preamble to C program example to tell about ABNF and alternative 
                     images. Removed meta-characters from comments (causes problems).
v06 2010-04-01 TT     Changed ipr attribute values to latest ones. Changed date to
                     year only, to be consistent with the comments. Updated the 
                     IANA guidelines reference from the I-D to the finished RFC.  

v1.1 Team Kronos Update Proposal pull request 2019-03-27 
	-Changed checksum to MD5 hash
	-Changed header fields to match descriptions, and changed checksum from INT to BUFFER
	-Added the packet transmission steps of the handshake (as they are defined in TCP) to the Technical Functionality
	-Added error handling for packets received with improper flag combinations (the packet is dropped)
                     
SETH NIELSON:
  Altered for PLAYGROUND AND PRFC's
  2016-09-21 SJN PRFC 1
  Updated for Fall 2017
  2017-10-1
  -->
 </back>
</rfc>
