<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is modified by Seth Nielson for creating P-RFC's
    (Playground-RFC's). -->
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
    which is available here: http://xml2rfc.ietf.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
    There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
    An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2360 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2360.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5226 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
    please see http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
    (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
    (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->




<rfc category="std" docName="rfc1" ipr="playgroundStd_v1_0" number="1">
 <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
    ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902,
       or pre5378Trust200902, playgroundWinter201501
    you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
    they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

 <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

 <front>
   <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
        full title is longer than 39 characters -->

   <title abbrev="PRFC's">Playground Request For Comments</title>

   <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

   <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

   <author fullname="Seth James Nielson" initials="S.J." role="editor"
           surname="Nielson">
     <organization>JHU Network Security Fall 2017</organization>

     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>JHU 160 Malone Hall/3400 North Charles St.</street>

         <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

         <city>Baltimore</city>

         <region>MD</region>

         <code>21218</code>

         <country>USA</country>
       </postal>

       <phone>+1 410-497-7384</phone>

       <email>sethjn@cs.jhu.edu</email>

       <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
     </address>
   </author>

   <date year="2019" />

   <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
        in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

   <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

   <area>General</area>

   <workgroup>Playground Experiment Director</workgroup>

   <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
        IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
        which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

   <keyword>PRFC</keyword>

   <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
        files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
        output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
        keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

   <abstract>
     <t>The PLAYGROUND (Poly-Localized Algorithmic Yields
     Generated Remotely On Unused Network Devices) system is
     designed to give students and researchers a sandbox in which to develop
     network security experiments. For PLAYGROUND experiments
     that involve a PETF (Playground Engineering Task Force),
     PRFC's (Playground RFC's) are used in a manner similar
     to RFC's. This PRFC specifices the format standards
     for PRFC's.</t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section title="Introduction">
     <t>RFC's (Request for Comments) are a publication of the Internet 
     Engineering Task Force (IETF). RFC's have many purposes including
     the publication of standards, general information, and best
     practices.</t>
     
     <t>The PLAYGROUND experiment, developed by Seth James Nielson,
     is a pedigogical framework for instructing principles of Internet
     Security. The primary goal of the PLAYGROUND framework is to provide
     a network system that allows students and researchers to develop
     security mechanisms as well as attacks against them. The PLAYGROUND
     system is designed to provide a complex enough system to enable
     kinds of attacks and defenses one finds in the real Internet but
     with a much reduced complexity.</t>
     
     <t>Not only does PLAYGROUND provide a reduced complexity, but it
     also allows a student to think in terms of principles instead of
     just in raw implementation. Cross-site scripting attacks may
     disappear in the future, but the principles of colliding security
     spaces will not. PLAYGROUND allows the students to try out principles
     in a new environment and with new concrete instantiations.</t>
     
     <t>Standards and other publications, such as RFC's, are a critical
     part of the security process. Open standards allow design flaws
     to be captured early in the development of an Internet protocol
     or system. Discovered flaws can be reported and fixed quickly
     and effectively.</t>
     
     <t>Accordingly, as part of the PLAYGROUND experiment, collaborating
     participants, such as the students in a class, can practice and
     experiment with a publication process similar to RFC's. These publications
     are called Playground RFC's and follow the same formats and
     serve the same purposes insofar as possible.</t>
     
     <t>This memo describes the PRFC standards, largely pointing to the
     corresponding standards for RFCs. Differences, where they exist,
     are noted. Also included is a description of a modified xml2rfc tool
     that can help to produce PRFC's with the proper formatting.</t>

     <section title="Requirements Language">
       <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
       "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
       document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
       target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
     </section>
   </section>
   
   <section title="General Authoring Guidelines">
    <t>The most important aspect of a PRFC is the clarity and correctness of
    the writing. The next most important component is the completeness of the
    technical document in describing all relevant information. The last and
    least important element is the formatting according to RFC guidelines.</t>
    
    <t>In terms of writing clearly and correctly, consider the following suggestions.</t>
    
    <t><list style="numbers">
    	<t>Use formal English grammar and use it correctly</t>
    	<t>Prefer conciseness and simplicity</t>
    	<t>Get to the point</t>
    </list></t>
    
    <t>Although the formatting is the least important element, authors SHOULD 
    learn and employ the correct formatting as much as possible. Most of this
    document will focus on these elements</t>
    
    <t>Authors MUST, after reading this PRFC, review any RFC's that are
    referenced. Authors SHOULD search for other RFC's that provide RFC-authoring
    guidelines or instructions as well as for other RFC-authoring guides and
    tutorials that can be found on the Internet.</t>
    
    <t>Astute readers will observe that this document is also not perfectly
    aligned with RFC standards and even technical writing guidelines. Similarly,
    it is not expected that other PRFC's will be perfect either. Nevertheless,
    authors MUST make good-faith efforts to understand the principles behind
    RFC documents and demonstrate them in crafting their own PRFC's.</t>
    
    <section title="Meta Data">
    <t>At the top of all PRFC's is meta-data analogous to the meta-data at the
    top of an RFC.</t>
    
    <t><list style="symbols">
    	<t>The PRFC SHOULD include the author's name.</t>
    	<t>The PRFC MUST identify "JHU Network Security Fall 2017" as the
    	organization</t>
    	<t>The PRFC MUST NOT identify a student's actual address. Use, instead,
    	a John Hopkins office number or laboratory name.</t>
    	<t>The PRFC MUST identify the month and year of writing.</t>
    </list></t>
    
    <t>Additional meta data includes the "References" and "Author's Address"
    sections. These elements MUST conform to RFC specifications.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Copyright Information">
    <t>The PLAYGROUND experiment is still new and has not yet developed
    a policy that has been reviewed by legal counsel. However, at present,
    the following text MUST be used in the PRFC's.</t>
    
    <t>The copyright notice on the front page of the PRFC should read:
    "Copyright (c) 2017 SETH JAMES NIELSON.  All rights reserved.</t>

   <t>This document is used solely for educational purposes.  Any citations
   within this document are also for educational purposes and also for
   technical reference.  If any of these cited elements are protected
   under copyright, their inclusion here falls under Fair Use
   provisions."</t>
   
   <t>Student authors MUST grant copyrights to SETH JAMES NIELSON. However,
   they may also retain copyrights for themselves and add their names to the
   copyright notice accordingly.</t>
   
   <t> The final page of the PRFC MUST include a section entitled 
   "Full Copyright Statement" that reads:</t>
   
   <t>"Copyright (C) Seth James Nielson (2017).  All Rights Reserved.</t>

   <t>This document and translations of it may be copied and furnished to
   others, and derivative works that comment on or otherwise explain it
   or assist in its implementation may be prepared, copied, published
   and distributed, in whole or in part, without restriction of any
   kind, provided that the above copyright notice and this paragraph are
   included on all such copies and derivative works.  However, this
   document itself may not be modified in any way, such as by removing
   the copyright notice or references to the PLAYGROUND experiment or
   other associated organizations, except by explicit permission.</t>

   <t>The limited permissions granted above are perpetual and will not be
   revoked by SETH JAMES NIELSON or his successors or assigns.</t>

   <t>This document and the information contained herein is provided on an
   "AS IS" basis and SETH JAMES NIELSON and associated academic
   institutions DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING
   BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE INFORMATION
   HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY RIGHTS OR ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
   MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE."</t>
   
   <t>After the "Full Copyright Statement" the PRFC MUST include a section
   entitled "Intellectual Property" that reads:</t>

   <t>The PLAYGROUND framework and student submissions for PLAYGROUND are
   intended to be free of any intellectual property conflicts.  All
   submitting parties, especially students, are not allowed to submit
   source code, specifications, or other components that are known to be
   protected by copyright, patents, or other IP mechanisms.  Students
   submitting creative content grant shared rights and ownership of
   their content to the PLAYGROUND project.  Specifically, any
   submission can be used in future educational settings including
   subsequent PLAYGROUND experiments.</t>

   <t>Any interested party is invited to bring to the experiment director's
   attention any copyrights, patents or patent applications, or other
   proprietary rights which may cover technology that may be currently
   in use without permission.</t>

   <t>It should be noted that these statements have not been reviewed by
   legal counsel.  Moreover, the academic institutions at which
   PLAYGROUND experiments take place may have additional or even
   conflicting copyright and intellectual property rules.  Accordingly,
   concerned parties may need to contact their own lawyer and/or
   resources at their institution to understand the rights and
   limitations associated with code donated to a PLAYGROUND experiment."</t>
   
   <t>As with the initial copyright notice, the Copyright assignment to
   Seth James Nielson can be agumented the the names of the authors.</t>
    </section>
    
	<section title="Guidelines for Writing Standards">
		<t>Most of the guidelines for writing standards are the same as they
		are for RFC's. In particular, <xref target="RFC2360">RFC 2360</xref>
		provides the current best practices for writing Internet Standards.
		In general, RFC 2360 will provide the basic template for evaluating 
		PRFC's that specify a standard.</t>
		
		<t>Perhaps the most important section of RFC 2360 is "2.1 Discussion of
		Security." Authors MUST read and understand this information. PRFC's without
		an adequate discussion of security will be rejected.</t>
		
		<t>Certain sections of RFC 2360 do not apply to writing PRFC's. These
		include:</t>
		
		<t><list style="empty">
			<t>2.5 Change Logs</t>
			<t>2.13 IANA Considerations</t>
			<t>2.14 Network Management Considerations</t>
			<t>2.17 Internationalization</t>
		</list></t>
		
		<t>For PRFC's that will serve as standards, the status MUST read: "
		This document specifies a Playgrounds standards track protocol for
   the Playground Experiment, and requests discussion and suggestions
   for improvements.  Distribution of this memo is unlimited."</t>
		
	</section>
	
	<section title="Guidlines for Writing Non-Standards">
		<t>PRFC's that are not standards track will not be held to the same
		requirements. In particular, while it would be great if these PRFC's
		tracked RFC guidelines, it is not required.</t>
		
		<t>For documents that comprise "best current practices," the status
		of the PRFC MUST read: "This document specifies an Playground Best Current Practices for the Playground
Experiment, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.
Distribution of this memo is unlimited."</t>

		<t>For documents that are for information purposes only, the status
		of the PRFC MUST read: "This memo provides information for the Playground Experiment.
It does not specify an Playground standard of any kind.
Distribution of this memo is unlimited."</t>

		<t>For documents that specify experimental protocols, 
		the status of the PRFC MUST read: "This memo defines an Experimental Protocol for the Playground Experiment.
It does not specify a Playground standard of any kind.
Discussion and suggestions for improvement are requested.
Distribution of this memo is unlimited."</t>

		<t>For documents that specify information that is kept for historical reasons
		the status of the PRFC must read: "This memo describes a historic protocol for the Playground Experiment.
It does not specify a Playground standard of any kind.
Distribution of this memo is unlimited."</t>
	</section>
   </section>
   
   <section title="PRFC Submission Process">
   <t>PRFC's are required whenever PLAYGROUND groups need to interoperate. Some 
   specifications will be mandated as part of PLAYGROUND development. Under these 
   circumstances, the PETF will be responsible for approving the standards.</t>
   
   <t>In creating these mandated standards, the PETF can either draft the standards
   and a reference implementation themselves or accept submissions from individual
   groups. In either case, the final standard must be approved by a majority of the
   PETF before the PRFC will be officially published.</t>
   
   <t>Any group can draft a standard that defines protocols and technologies that
   are specific to their own PLAYGROUND nodes. Publishing PRFC's is the only acceptable
   way for two groups to interact with each other. Thus, if a group wishes to make
   their optional mechanisms available to other groups, they must create a PRFC 
   publication. These PRFC's do not need the approval of the PETF if they are given
   "experimental" status. Otherwise, a majority of the PETF must approve the standard
   in order for it to be given "standards-track" status.</t>
   
   <t>PRFC's seeking "informational" status also do not require PETF approval.</t>
   
   <t>PRFC's seeking "best current practice" status do require PETF approval.</t>
   </section>
   
   <section title="PRFC Revision Process">
   <t>Once a PRFC is officially published by the PETF, it cannot be modified further
   for any reason. A new PRFC must be submitted that identifies the errors and 
   proposes to "update" or "supercede" the previous document.</t>
   
   <t>A PRFC MUST use the "update" reference if the changes do not result in an
   incompatible protocol and the old protocol is not shown to be insecure. 
   Changes to PRFC's that are "updates" include:</t>
   
   <t><list style="numbers">
   	<t>Corrections to spelling, grammar, and other wording in the document</t>
   	<t>Additional details about operations and operational considerations</t>
   	<t>Additional parameters or interactions to the existing protocol</t>
   </list></t>
   
   <t>A PRFC MUST use the "supercede" reference if the changes result in an incompatible
   protocol OR if the previous protocol is demonstrated to be insecure.</t>
   
   <t>Approval from the PETF MUST be obtained if approval was required for the original
   PRFC.</t>
   
   <t>A PRFC submitted without PETF approval MUST be revised only by the same PLAYGROUND
   group that submitted the original.</t>
   </section>
   
   <section title="Security Considerations">
   <t>This specification is a documentation standard and not directly related
   to the technical security of any protocol.</t>
   </section>
 </middle>

 <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

 <back>
   <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

   <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
    1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
    2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
       (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

    Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
    If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
    directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
    with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
    filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

   <references title="Normative References">
     <!--?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
     &RFC2119;
     
     &RFC2360;
     
   </references>


   <!-- Change Log

v00 2006-03-15  EBD   Initial version

v01 2006-04-03  EBD   Moved PI location back to position 1 -
                     v3.1 of XMLmind is better with them at this location.
v02 2007-03-07  AH    removed extraneous nested_list attribute,
                     other minor corrections
v03 2007-03-09  EBD   Added comments on null IANA sections and fixed heading capitalization.
                     Modified comments around figure to reflect non-implementation of
                     figure indent control.  Put in reference using anchor="DOMINATION".
                     Fixed up the date specification comments to reflect current truth.
v04 2007-03-09 AH     Major changes: shortened discussion of PIs,
                     added discussion of rfc include.
v05 2007-03-10 EBD    Added preamble to C program example to tell about ABNF and alternative 
                     images. Removed meta-characters from comments (causes problems).

v06 2010-04-01 TT     Changed ipr attribute values to latest ones. Changed date to
                     year only, to be consistent with the comments. Updated the 
                     IANA guidelines reference from the I-D to the finished RFC.  
                     
SETH NIELSON:
  Altered for PLAYGROUND AND PRFC's
  2016-09-21 SJN PRFC 1

  Updated for Fall 2017
  2017-10-1
  -->
 </back>
</rfc>
